Leah: So, what are the disadvantages
of writing complicated code?
Teams of professional programmers
often collaborate on projects,
where it is very common that other
people will need to view their code.
This could be to review it, extend
it, or even just to understand it,
in order to write other parts of the
program which are dependent on it.
To try to mitigate some of the
problems caused by complicated code,
there are many coding practices
and conventions which have been
developed to try to standardise code.
One example is ‘PEP8 for Python’.
This is a document that provides
guidelines and best practices
to improve the readability and
consistency of coding in Python.
For more information on
this check out our weblink.
Jack: So, what are the
disadvantages of complicated
coding and the effects it can have.
First let’s look how
this affects Variables
If ‘variable names are too
long’ this can clutter code
If ‘variable names are not descriptive’,
they are ambiguous to what the
variable holds or its function.
If ‘variable names are not
standardised’, you might not be
able to tell what sort of variable
it is, for example local or global.
There are however conventions for this
in some languages such as capitalization,
prefixed or suffixed with an underscore.
Leah: So, now let’s look at
how this affects ‘Functions’
Say a ‘function name is undescriptive’
you might not be able to tell what
the function is supposed to do.
‘Functions may become bloated,
non-specific, and have side effects’.
Functions should generally
serve one purpose, and not
affect other code sections.
It can make debugging difficult
when a function is not constrained.
‘Functions are not generalised’.
If functions are not written to be
general, you may end up with many
functions which serve a similar purpose,
and this can make code confusing.
‘Too many lines of code are replaced with
functions.’ Replacing sections of code
with functions can be useful when this
particular operation needs to occur a lot.
However, this can confuse code and
complicate debugging if the function is
only called once or is only a single line.
Jack: Now let’s look at the
what the effect is on Comments
‘Comments are missing in code’.
If there are no comments in a
confusing section of code, then
its purpose may be unclear.
‘Comments describing functions are
missing, unstandardised or too long’.
Many languages have conventions
which describe a function.
This usually includes a short
description of what it does, and the
data types, and also short descriptions
of the inputs, and the outputs.
This is called a 'docstring’ and
if it is missing, unstandardised,
or too long, it can take longer
for coders to resolve problems.
As a program develops, it
often becomes more complex.
It is therefore crucial, especially in
the early stages, to keep code clean
and accessible in order to ensure that
it is maintainable and understandable
when someone comes back to it.